foreign
[Music]
thank you and grateful to you for
spending so much time with us here this
evening I'm going to take a little bit
more uh so if you could please be seated
uh it's always wonderful to hear from
you and you gave us a very uh sort of
comprehensive synopsis of what you
believe the road ahead for India looks
like I know you've said this previously
in interviews that we've done that it is
a 25-year Runway that you believe India
has the ability to enjoy uh you also
gave us a very quick synopsis of what
the world looks like today and I want to
pick up on some of these issues that you
spoke of in the context of another event
that we are going to be marking and it's
a pretty significant Milestone that we
will be marking uh this week itself
where India will overtake China in
becoming the most populous country in
the world and it has its advantages and
it has its downsides as well you talked
about productivity gains you talked
about technology and Technology adoption
uh you know we often speak of our
demographic Advantage how do you see
this Milestone and what you believe it
means from a risk perspective especially
when we talk about the India story over
the next 25 years
it's a very appropriate question at this
point in time the first thought that
comes to your mind is it's a positive
for a very simple reason if we were at a
stage where we would have built a lot of
things that we need to build I would
have said uh you know we could be facing
a challenge but given that by all
assessments we have a 25-year Runway to
build essential things we are not
talking of anything esoteric to build
essential things we need the people and
we need a young population
we needed young population not only to
build but also to consume and I think
that provides us a unique advantage in
terms of having the the forces it were
to build and having the ability to
consume what we are producing of course
we will export uh as we go along but I
do not necessarily believe that we will
export the way some other countries have
been exporting because we have a large
domestic Market under the growth rate
that we're going you can well afford to
have a domestic content consumption as a
primary driver and exports as a
subsidiary set so this comes in at the
right time okay you believe it comes in
at the right time but I'll just press
you a little bit more on that so you
talked about the consumption power and
specifically the the consumption power
of the domestic economy and while we are
seeing Investments pick up and continues
to be largely driven by government capex
at this point in time the question
though is for this young population are
we going to be able to provide the kinds
of jobs that we need to especially in an
era where you're talking about the
possibility of chat GPT taking over jobs
making automated jobs redundant uh or
making jobs redundant on account of
automation the impact of that do you
believe it is going to be as many
headlines as suggesting a pop ecliptic
or do you believe that this is something
uh that we will be able to digest as we
move forward I think uh nothing is
static things uh keep moving I would
still talk of the India advantage and
let me put one thing in context five
years back who would have believed that
India would be such a such a big um I
did a very simple term back office to
the world you know call it managed
services or whatever so much so that uh
everyone is caught by surprise I wasn't
I can tell you when we say that our
services exports and our not only you
know probably the fastest growing side
of sports but we now are a net Surplus
on that everybody thought that we will
keep spending money on paying royalty
payments and so on so that's termed a
positive so if these uh for example just
staying on managed Services if this vast
number of jobs are going to be created
here we need people to run those so
maybe if there's a shift away from some
of the other things because you know
people may not be required because
technology has evolved but in the newer
things that are coming onshore uh
through this process of back office is
being set up here I'm just seeing one
example and when you talk of these back
offices these are not we're not talking
of thousand two thousand people we are
talking of just now you know people are
talking of virtually in running into
hundreds or thousands of people so I
think things will know you all and then
when you talk of a person you remember
when the first wave of white collar I
would say
momentum was seen in the country 2000
2001. chrysala done yesterday I remember
that for every white collar job created
four new uh jobs in the service sector
were created around it these may not be
full jobs there could be partial jobs I
see the same thing happening as these
white collar jobs are proliferated so
I'm not worried about that and then I
think we also need to look at just look
at the last two or three years the the
the number of uh Provident fund uh you
know registered people if you look at
these uh it tells me a different story
and having the
Field Force as it were is a big plus
yeah
Plus I want to you know pick up on some
of the things that you spoke up and you
talked about of course your favorite
subject which is uh the fact that there
possibly needs to be a rewriting of
economic theory when we talk about
linking inflation and interest rates I
know that you have uh for a while now
believe that the RBI and the MPC don't
need to hike interest rates like the
West is hiking at this point in time uh
it is a hard pause or that is what we're
given to understand that the MPC has
taken at this point in time where do you
see interest rates at least in India in
the near term no I see when I was a
practicing Banker I never commented on
this but now now you have now open about
it I'm sure you know maybe lay person I
can say a few things but I think the RBA
has done absolutely uh the right thing
in uh over the last three years not one
misstep so I can't blame uh I do not
know what happens in the MPC but some
total that's what you have seen I think
they take India's taking a right stand
the issue that I have is with the West
economic theory that's coming out of the
West which in earlier periods influenced
us and now when it comes there turn
their happily uh saying you know that
doesn't matter
uh so I think we need to understand
everything that the West says may not be
appropriate for us and we need to apply
our mind and see what is right and do
what is right so that was uh my context
in what I had said on this but there's
another aspect to this
today if you see the adverse impact of a
rate increase could possibly be more
harmful than what we thought for example
if you look at a bank today probably 70
percent of it of its assets that it
holds are retail assets or if there's an
Emi and you have a situation where you
have a rate increase it could push a
whole lot of that repayment Beyond
retirement so these are all risks which
uh when we today we are talking of risk
we need to be put into context when we
look at this I'm sure RBI does it but
what I'm asking is does the larger body
of Economist actually look at this is
are there concrete numbers is this
worked out is there a spreadsheet or
whatever algorithm that you worked out
to say what is the impact in the
consequence of this not just look at one
indicator look at it as a multivariate
and then let us see I'm sure that the
bank has done this but I want a theory
on this uh which is exported here or
outside I would think the same thing
would apply today to the U.S so far
they're not bothered because with the
sort of rate increases that you see on
the mortgage front from a year year and
a half back a mortgage was around trend
of four percent today you're talking of
seven and a half percent how many people
would move Beyond retirement in terms of
it I have not yet seen the numbers
these are things that today need to be
crunched into economic theory I am
talking a pure economic theory that
comes out of schools to understand and
appreciate and I'm not saying that in
India which is unfortunate
well you know I'm gonna uh take your
view and your opinion on what we're
seeing happen as far as the global
banking sector is concerned because you
were very clear about the fact that the
Indian banking sector today along with
corporate India is far more resilient uh
balance sheets have strength we've just
come off record numbers for a whole
bunch of banks including ICICI Bank for
this quarter uh but you know on what is
happening with global banks at this
point in time a jaw-dropping number a
100 billion dollar deposit plunge for
First Republic blank uh you know what do
you make of this and the long-term
implications of the medium-term
implications of how this is likely to
panic straight forward answer is that it
indicates that uh again vast holes in
the risk management practices by both
Regulators there and the banks
themselves
uh and uh you know when this happened I
went into the balance sheet of that
particular bank and what struck me was I
read it three times I went into the
piano the piano has got a profit nice
profit and the npas are in business
points not even percentage points you
come to the balance sheet item number
two is uh uh you know held to maturity
instruments within brackets the
valuation is given the value is shown as
almost 100 and within brackets Uh
current valuation was 84. so I said am I
reading right and previous year it was
97 or something like that so whereas
this what has happened then did it
tracked me that this is where the hole
is and it's not accounted for it is just
a line item so if this is how you are
looking at risk you know basically uh
you are I'm sure there are lessons which
have been learned I do not know the you
know how other Regulatory and other
domains look at it but this is not true
in India so I can be proud of what is in
India this sort of a thing can never
happen in India
so that gives me confidence to say apart
from you know Capital adequacy which is
in High Teens uh pristine NPA net NPA
levels lower than in some banks quarter
percent
and then this sort of a very tight risk
management practices I think makers one
of the safest banking systems anywhere
well that's good to hear uh you know you
were talking about the role The
Regulators have played and you believe
that that's been a stellar performance
uh here in India uh in terms of what we
are seeing play out in the domestic
context but more importantly also around
the world
if there were one or two areas where you
believe there needs to be strengthening
of regulatory oversight uh what would
those be in India specifically no I I
would think that today specifically the
needle is moved to corporates who are
the borrowers and individuals who are
the borrowers where there may be a need
for educating the borrower as to what is
good and right and this is not
necessarily in the banking space is it
it is entire in entire Financial
Services space where people are you know
sometimes almost coaxed to say that well
it doesn't matter you get on your app
and you swipe left or right and the deal
is done a deal is not done you are
basically building risk on your balance
sheet as a consequence I think so both
sides people who are providing this sort
of a product and on the other side
people are consuming it ought to be uh
you know educated in a way similarly if
uh you know on a corporate front there
is a mismatched uh you know
lending happening is not linked to your
Alco situation and borrowing also on the
same basis I think you're exposing
yourself to risks when an event like you
know pile fluctuation interest rate
happens so I think there is a better
there is Need for better understanding
of risk even in your borrowing book not
lending book in your borrowing book uh
in the corporate world and I think
gentle education probably is required
not necessarily where you are but at the
retail individual end I think something
more dramatic needs to be uh probably
done what more dramatic change would you
like to see it says that I would put it
very simply as uh to heighten the risk
anybody puts out an ad saying XYZ I
think the regulator should have come out
and say that these are the risks or
asset company to spell out the risk very
clearly and not in that blinding speed
at what bottom where you say that like
in the public issue they used to say
that subject to Market risk it's not low
along the case I'm taking it as an
example but in ads which are you know
propounding that well there is no risk
in your transaction I think there needs
to be a counter
[Music]